xtramath.org 2019-05-15

# XtraMath Privacy Policy

XtraMath Privacy Policy
Introduction
XtraMath is committed to protecting data privacy. We strictly adhere to this Privacy Policy, which
explains what user data we collect and how we use it. This policy and our ​Terms of Service​ are
known collectively as our “Terms.” We may change these Terms from time to time, but will
provide notice as specified in the Terms of Service document.
This policy is effective May 25, 2018, and replaces our ​prior privacy policy​.
Summary
    ●  We collect ​the minimum amount of data required to operate our
       program.
    ●  We use parents’ and teachers’ Personal Data to operate our program and, with their
       permission, to contact them about the program.
    ●  We use students’ Personal Data only to operate our program.
    ●  We use de-identified student data to improve our program.
    ●  We protect student data and have signed the ​Student Privacy Pledge​.
    ●  We do not advertise to students, sell their data, or profile them in any way.
    ●  We comply with applicable data privacy laws, such as FERPA, COPPA, and GDPR.
    ●  We never sell user data to third parties.
What Data We Collect
XtraMath collects the minimum amount of data required to operate our program. Below we
summarize the data we collect on students, teachers, and parents. For an up-to-date list that
shows what user data we collect, and how we use that data, see Appendix B, ​Record of Data
Processing​.
Definitions
    ●  Data​ includes all information connected with a person’s or educational entity’s use of
       XtraMath. This includes, but is not limited to, Personal Data, metadata, usage and
       performance data.
    ●  Personal Data​ includes any data that can directly or indirectly identify an individual
       person. For example: an email address is always considered Personal Data; a student’s
       grade level generally is not, but could be in conjunction with other information.
                                                                                               1 of 9

    ●   School​ includes: individual schools; teachers acting on behalf of schools; school
        districts; and other local educational entities.
Student Data
We collect a student’s first name, grade level, and program settings from the student’s parent or
teacher. As the student uses XtraMath, we collect usage and performance data, such as when
they signed in, how many questions they answered correctly, and how long it took them to
answer questions. If a student signs in via a single sign-on provider, such as Google, we collect
an identifier from the provider that allows us to authenticate their sign-in. We do ​not​ collect the
student email address that may be used for such a sign-in.
Other personal information about the student could be inferred from data that we collect. If a
student account belongs to a class, for example, then we could infer that they attend a certain
school.
Parent Data
We collect a parent’s name and email address when they sign up for an account. If they sign up
using a single sign-on provider, we also collect an identifier that allows us to authenticate their
sign-in. We also collect some metadata and account settings, such as their time zone, the
language they used to sign up, and their email preferences.
A parent supplies a password when they create an account. The password is hashed
(scrambled) on the user’s computer before it is ever sent to XtraMath. We do not have access to
a user’s original password, and cannot obtain it from the hashed version that we receive.
Other personal information about the parent could be inferred from data that we collect. For
example, we could infer that a parent whose account is linked to a student account is the parent
or guardian of that student.
Teacher Data
We collect the same data for teacher accounts as parent accounts, with a few additions. For
example, we collect the name by which students address the teacher, such as “Ms. Smith.” We
also collect information about each class that the teacher creates, such as its name and its end
date.
Other personal information about the teacher could be inferred from data we collect. For
example, we could infer that the teacher works at a specific school based on their email
address.
                                                                                                 2 of 9

How We Use and Share Data
XtraMath processes user data in order to establish and maintain accounts, to provide
educational activities to students, to compile and deliver reports about those activities to
teachers and parents, and to understand and improve our program’s effectiveness. For an
up-to-date list that shows the specific types of user data we collect, and how we use that data,
see Appendix B, ​Record of Data Processing​.
Student Data
A student’s Personal Data is used internally to provide the student with appropriate educational
activities, and to report their performance to their parents and teachers. We may access student
Personal Data when providing customer support or investigating a reported issue with our
program.
Parent and Teacher Data
A parent’s or teacher’s Personal Data is used internally for sign-in purposes and, with
permission, to send them reports, announcements, and alerts related to XtraMath. We may
access a parent’s or teacher’s Personal Data when providing them with requested support.
Sharing Personal Data with Third Parties
We release Personal Data to third parties only in the following circumstances:
    ●    When the user requests the disclosure​, such as a teacher sharing their class with
         another teacher.
    ●    When the third party is a trusted service provider​, and the data is required to adequately
         perform the service. We carefully vet our service providers and their security practices.
         For details, see Appendix A, ​List of Third Party Providers​.
    ●    When required by law or a court order​.
    ●    In the event of a joint venture, sale or merger with a third party​. The third party would be
         required to uphold our Terms, including our Privacy Policy for all existing accounts. We
         would provide advance notice before sharing data with that third party.
XtraMath never releases Personal Data for any kind of third-party advertising.
Use of De-identified Data
We may use de-identified usage data internally to analyze and improve our educational
services, and to develop new products or features. We will never attempt to re-identify data that
has been de-identified.
                                                                                                  3 of 9

We may release de-identified data to educational researchers for the purpose of evaluating the
effectiveness of our program. We will not release de-identified data unless we are confident it
cannot be re-identified, due to the removal of all direct and indirect personal identifiers, and the
educational researchers have agreed in writing that they will not attempt to re-identify any
individuals, classes, or Schools.
We may use aggregate de-identified data, such as the number of users of our service, for
promotional purposes.
How We Securely Store Data
XtraMath takes security seriously. We implement a variety of industry-standard security
measures to prevent any unauthorized access to our users’ data. Such measures include, but
are not limited to: data minimization; encrypting data in transit via HTTPS; hashing sensitive
data, like passwords; deletion of outdated data; locked physical facilities; employee training; and
administrator account security.
Data Storage and International Transfer
XtraMath stores and processes all data on servers in the United States. All servers that store
XtraMath data are operated by trusted third party processors with whom we have contractual
Data Processing Addendums. Our providers are certified under the ​EU-US Privacy Shield and
Swiss-US Privacy Shield​, to better protect the data of our international users. For details, see
Appendix A, ​List of Third Party Providers​.
Data Breach Response
While we use industry-standard practices to safeguard data, no service can guarantee absolute
data security. We have a Breach Response Plan, which we will follow if we ever discover that
Personal Data has been accessed improperly. As part of our response, we will: take action to
stop further data loss or unauthorized access; investigate how the breach occurred; promptly
contact all affected users via email; and contact law enforcement and government agencies
when appropriate.
Data Retention and Deletion
XtraMath retains Personal Data only for as long as necessary to ensure continuity of math
skill-building for students, and for the convenience of parents and teachers. We close user
accounts, and delete all associated identifiable data, upon request. Most types of data are also
deleted automatically after a certain amount of time has passed. For details, see Appendix B,
Record of Data Processing​.
                                                                                                4 of 9

We may retain de-identified, aggregate data, which cannot identify any individual user, for
research and program improvement purposes. Such data is deleted once no longer necessary
for these purposes.
We will provide certification of data deletion upon request.
Compliance with Data Privacy Laws
XtraMath intends to comply with the data privacy and data protection laws of all jurisdictions
where it operates. See the XtraMath and Student Data Privacy whitepaper for the latest
information on compliance. Some specific examples of legislation that we comply with are
described below.
United States
Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA): ​As a non-profit organization, XtraMath is
not subject to ​COPPA​. Nevertheless, we fully comply with the law as if we were subject to it.
Children under the age of 13 may not create accounts. We only collect usage and performance
data from students as a result of their performing educational activities, and we only use that
data for educational purposes. If we gain actual knowledge that a child is using XtraMath
without the appropriate consent, we terminate the account.
Family Education Rights Protection Act (FERPA):​ Schools in the United States may provide
student data to XtraMath while complying with ​FERPA​. When a School provides us with a
student’s Personal Data (or PII — Personally Identifiable Information) under the FERPA school
official exemption, they remain in control of that data. XtraMath will only use and disclose that
data as specified in our Terms and as allowed by law.
International
General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)​: XtraMath affirms and respects all data subject's
rights under ​GDPR​. We minimize the data we collect and process, and use data only as
described in this policy. For detailed information about what data we process, for what purpose,
for how long, and our basis for doing so under the GDPR, see Appendix B, ​Record of Data
Processing​. To object to processing, or to request data deletion or access, contact our Data
Protection Officer at ​privacy@xtramath.org​.
                                                                                              5 of 9

Cookies and Local Storage
XtraMath intends to discontinue the use of cookies by August 1, 2018.
XtraMath uses two types of cookies. These cookies can be cleared via browser settings —
aboutcookies.org​ provides cookie management instructions for many specific browsers.
    ●    Google Analytics​ cookies allow us to see data such as the number of site visitors we
         get, and which pages they visit the most.
    ●    Vimeo ​cookies are stored when users play the videos on our homepage, and primarily
         keep track of the video player settings.
The XtraMath website uses “LocalStorage” files to remember a user’s sign-in information (if they
choose to do so). We also use “SessionStorage” to improve performance during student
activities by temporarily storing activity data on the device. Use of LocalStorage and
SessionStorage is not required to use XtraMath. Users can remove remembered sign-in
information at any time via the appropriate sign-in page. Users can also clear all LocalStorage
by using the “Clear now” button on our ​support page​, or via browser settings.
The XtraMath mobile apps use application data for the same purposes as browser LocalStorage
and SessionStorage. Users can still remove remembered sign-in information via the app’s
sign-in pages. Uninstalling the app will remove all locally stored data. Some devices also allow
users to clear locally stored app data without uninstalling the app.
Contact Us
For data privacy questions or concerns, to object to processing, or to request access to or
deletion of your or your child’s Personal Data, email us at ​privacy@xtramath.org​. You may also
write to us at: XtraMath, 4700 42nd Ave SW #580, Seattle, WA 98116
                                                                                            6 of 9

Appendix A: List of Third Party Providers
This list will be kept up-to-date to include all third-party providers with which XtraMath shares
user data.
 Provider       Data shared with Provider     Purpose                          Relevant Policies
 Name
 AWS            User account data, including  Database hosting via remote      Privacy Policy
                name, email address, and      servers
                program usage.
 Google         Anonymous ID created by       Website analytics                Privacy Policy
                cookie                                                         Opt-out Browser Add-on
 MaxMind        IP address                    Geolocation service              Privacy Policy
 Vimeo          Anonymous ID created by       Enable playback of embedded      Privacy Policy
                cookie, video player settings videos (remember volume, if
                                              video is paused, etc)
                                                                                                 7 of 9

Appendix B: Record of Data Processing
We have compiled this record in order to provide users with as much transparency as possible
into how we use their data. This record also helps us to comply with European law. Unless
otherwise noted in the record below, we process user data based on our legitimate interests.
 Account     Type of Data               Processing Purpose                Deletion
 Type
             First name, PIN, parent or Account access and identification Upon account closure​1​.
             teacher email, class                                         Some information is
                                                                          deleted upon removal
                                                                          from the class or linked
                                                                          account.
             Single-sign-on provider    Account access using optional     Upon request or account
             and hashed ID              3rd party credential              closure​1
             Grade level                Determine initial activity level. Upon account closure​1
                                        When de-identified and
 Student                                aggregated, used to analyze
                                        program usage.
             Program settings: current  Activity customization. When      Upon account closure​1
             program, UI options,       de-identified and aggregated,
             preferred language, etc.   used to analyze program usage.
             Activity data              Activity customization and        Upon account closure​1​.
                                        creation of progress reports.     Some data is deleted
                                        When de-identified and            when user restarts a
                                        aggregated, used to analyze       program. Detailed
                                        program usage.                    activity data is deleted
                                                                          after one year.
             Name, “addressed as”       Account access and identification Upon account closure​2, 3
             name, email address,
             hashed password
             Email address              Send announcements, alerts,       Processing ceases upon
                                        reports, and/or reminders via     request. Data deletion
 Parent or                              email                             upon account closure​2, 3
 Teacher
             Email address              Share with linked accounts that   Data deletion upon
                                        have access to same student or    account closure​2, 3
                                        class (for increased transparency
                                        and security of student data)
             Account settings: account  Create progress reports and       Upon account closure​2, 3
             type, email preferences,   maintain data preferences
             time zone, etc.
                                                                                                8 of 9

             Electronic identifiers:   Technical support and account      Upon account closure​2, 3
             account change            security
             timestamps, version
             number, etc.
Parent or    Single-sign-on provider   Account access using optional      Upon request or account
Teacher      and hashed ID             3rd party credential               closure​2, 3
             IP address                Determine time zone upon           Not stored
                                       sign-up
             Hashed IP address         Account security                   After 1 year or upon
                                                                          account closure​2, 3
             Hashed IP address         Expedite classroom setup on        After 24 hours
                                       multiple devices
Teacher      Class name, class end     Create progress reports and        Upon request, account
             date, student names       facilitate program usage           closure​3​, or one year
                                                                          after class end date.
             Hashed IP address,        Network security                   After 90 days
             change logs
All Users
             De-identified and         Product improvement and            Until no longer useful
             aggregated usage data     development, promotional
                                       activities, and educational
                                       research
    1. Student accounts: account closure occurs upon request, automatically after two years of
       account inactivity, or one month after being unlinked from all parent and teacher
       accounts.
    2. Parent accounts: account closure occurs upon request, or automatically after two years
       of account inactivity.
    3. Teacher accounts: account closure occurs upon request.
                                                                                                9 of 9
